<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine questions by way of conference betwixt a chauncelor and a kinswoman of his concerning the churching of women</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1601</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 37 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10269</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 20557</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S105979</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841704</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841704</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6302</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10269)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6302)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1639:08)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine questions by way of conference betwixt a chauncelor and a kinswoman of his concerning the churching of women</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>74 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>R. Schilders],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1601.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication and printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Some print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Women --  Religious life.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Jayanthi Reddy</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6302:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Certaine Queſtions by way of Conference betwixt a Chauncelor and a Kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man of his concerning <hi>Churching of Women.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1601.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="dialogue">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:6302:2"/>
            <head>Certeine questions by way of conference betwixt a Chauncelor and a kinſwoman of his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning <hi>Churching of Women.</hi>
            </head>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>TRulie Couſen I am ſorie that you ſhould thus vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a pieviſh conceite of yours bring your ſelf into this vn-neceſſarie trouble for a trifle and matter of nothing as it were.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>If you be ſorie indeed as you pretende, then you might haue let me alone, and not haue cauſed your Apparitor to ſerue me (as he did) with Citation, for aſſure your ſelfe if you had not troubled me, I would never haue troubled my ſelfe about this trifle you ſpeake of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nay I muſt not do ſo, I muſt deale indifferentlie you know, and not be partiall though you be my kinſwo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:6302:2"/>Th'information being againſt you as well as others, &amp; your name being prese<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ted to me by the church Wardens with other women moe, if I ſhould leaue you out and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed againſt them, I ſhould not doe that which were fitting for my place and office, you know I am ſworne to doe iuſtice.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Indeed your office and place afoordes much iustice, if it be well obſerved, as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie iustice as Billinſgate doeth loue &amp; friendſhip for a boxe of th'eare: you are ſworne you ſaye, and will not that oath of yours alow you to ſhew as much favor and kindneſſe to your kinſwoman in a trifle, as to a ſtranger that is no kinne to you in a matter of weight?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O I knowe where you are now, I thought where you would bee ſtraight, I knew I ſhould heare of it, you meane miſtres</hi> A.B. <hi>But in good faith your Miniſter did her wrong, neither had he anie law to warrant
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:6302:3"/>him to doe that he vrged her vnto: I co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe ſhe made a fault before ſhe was maried, but the man you know made her amendes, and I doe not heare but that they liue orderly and well nowe: notwithſtandinge all which your hotte ſpirited Miniſter (of ſpight &amp; malice as itis thought) would haue put them both to open penance, if I had not ſtucke cloſe to them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Mercifull Christ, what neede anie wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to be produced againſt you, when your owne mouth doeth ſo apparantlie co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne you? The gentlewoman you confeſſe made a fault: and what was that fault but ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple Fornicatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> at the least? For the which our Miniſter would haue done that which belonged vnto him, if you would haue lett him, and that whiche I take it (by your leaue) the Booke of common Prayer it ſelfe doeth warrant him to doe, and you by your owne confeſsion withstoode him in that good purpoſe of his. Nowe ſurely (my good
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:6302:3"/>man) this is a ſinne amongest others that you must repent of, otherwiſe it wilbe woe with you. And I pray you tel me one thing: Mistres <hi>A. B.</hi> is a ſtraunger to you and I am your kinſwoman, her fault (cover it &amp; ſhadow it as you will) was vncleanneſſe at the least, and that which you trouble mee for, is but a Ceremonie, &amp; as your ſelf con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, a matter of no moment. What war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant haue you then ſo ſtiflie to ſtande with her in her ſinne, and to deale thus ſharplie with me and others in a thing indifferent, or a matter of nothing?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well gentle kinſwoman, ſeeing you are ſo ſnappiſh &amp; over-buſying yourſelf in other folkes matters that apperteine not vnto you, I pray you let me heare now how handſomely you can anſwere for your ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>With whoſe matters did I medle I pray you, did not you firſt name mistreſſe <hi>A. B.</hi> your ſelfe?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>All is one for that, I know you meant her when you ſaid, that my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:6302:4"/>oath might as well alow me to ſhew fauour to my kinſwoman in a trifle, as to a ſtra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ger in a matter of weight.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well be it ſo then: If your conſcience did accuſe you, looke you to that: But what haue you now to ſay to me, and what is the cauſe why you haue ſent for me?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You neede not aske, you know it well enough I am ſure. It is for your fooliſh niceneſſe in this trifling mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Churching. And I pray you in good ſadneſſe, what reaſon haue you why you refuſe to be Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>If it be as you ſay a trifle, the more to blame you to trouble your friends in ſo tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fling a cauſe: But what doe you meane by Churching? Doe you meane that which is ſett downe in the Booke?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iuſt, I meane that and none other: For law will not warrant vs to preſſe you to any other?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>No nor I thinke to that neither if it be well examined: But ſeeing you meane
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:6302:4"/>that kinde of Churching, The reaſon in a woord why I refuſe it is this: Becauſe I would be loth to ſhew my ſelfe either Iew or Papist.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why will thankeſgiuing to God after Childbirth make you a lew or a Papiſt?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>No: Thankeſgiuing will not: But this manner of thankeſgiving that you would haue me to obſerue is in trueth no thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving at all, but a meere Iewiſh or Popiſh Purifying.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How doe you proove it to be no thankeſgiuing?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>By the verie first inſtitution of it: For the Papistes that were the woorſhipfull founders and deviſers of it, and knew best their own meaning, did in the instituting of it, giue it this title: <hi>The Purification of Women after Childbirth.</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it is manifest that their very drift and intent in th'inſtitution was only for a Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification or Purging, and therefore no thankeſgiving: Secondly, there is no one
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:6302:5"/>woord, matter or forme of thankeſgiuing in the whole order of it as it is ſet downe in the booke: and therefore it can not be that it was ordayned for Thankeſgivinge. though in the title thereof it be abſurdlie ſo called.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But why doe you tearme it a Iew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh or a Popiſh Purifying?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>It is Iewiſh in <hi>2</hi> reſpectes: Firſt in that the woman after ſhe hath brought foorth a childe, is held vncleane (as vnder the Law) til ſuch time as ſhe hath ſhewed her<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in the Temple. Secondlie in that ſhee is commanded to offer her accustomed of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feringes, which is drawen &amp; deriued from the Lamb and young Pigeons vnder the Law. Popiſh it is in <hi>3</hi> reſpectes: First in that it was inſtituted and deviſed by the Rapiſtes, apiſhlie imitating the Iewes, and bringing in one kinde of Purifying in ſteade of another. Secondly in that the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is commaunded to come as neare the communion table, as in the time of popery they came to the high Altar. Laſtlie, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:6302:5"/>of the Popiſh offeringe, to weete the Chriſome: For ſhe is commaunded to of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer th'accuſtomed offeringes, which is ſete downe to be the Chriſome, In which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard you may as inſtlie trouble me and cal me hither for not offering the Chriſome, as for not being purifyed, and as good law you haue for th'one as th'other, whiche makes me thinke (as I ſayed before) that you haue no law amongeſt you (but onelie the lawleſſe law of your will and pleaſure) to compell any woman to be Churched.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, wee will talke of that ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther time: but I would to God, yee fooliſh women would medle with that whiche belongs vnto you, and which is within the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>paſſe of your owne element, and not take vppon you the deciſion and interpretation of the law, which ye vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d not: But I pray you tell me one thinge, what if the Church now would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute and ordeyne a ſolemne</hi> Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying <hi>of women, would you not bee
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:6302:6"/>purified?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>No indeed would I not: For if I ſhould, I ſhould then either with the Iewes denie Christ to be come in the fleſhe to giue an end to thoſe ſhadowes which were figures of the purifying and waſhing away of our ſinnes by his bloud, or els with the Papiſtes I muſt denie the bloudſhead and ſufferings of Chriſt to be th'only and alone ſufficient purgation, of ſinne, and therefore it is that we must haue a ſupply and be fart her hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen by ſome Church Ceremonie, or out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward forme of Prayers out of the mouth of ſome ſhaveling or Priest.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea, but ſee now I pray you how you are deceyved in the heate of your zeale, looke in the booke there is no ſuch matter of</hi> Purifying <hi>as you ſpeake of, but onelie of</hi> Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Truſt me, you ſay true, I had almoſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten that it ſpeaketh not a woord indeed of Purifying. But what a iugling &amp; blea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of th'eis of the ſimple is this amongst
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:6302:6"/>you. May we not heerein ſay of you &amp; your fellowes, that yee are the most perillous in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumentes, and dangerous impoſtors that euer Sathan rayſed vp for th'advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and restoring againe of Poperie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why ſo I pray you my good kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman? What neede all this heate among friendes? You ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine belike you are amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g your ſcol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding dames and pratling huſwiues at home?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>No good Maister Chauncelor, I know I thanke God where I am, neither am I any whitte distempered at all: But that whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che I haue ſayed, I may truly and lawful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſay againe: In which regard well fare the Papistes ſay I, for they ſhall riſe vp in iudgement againſt you, who like good fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes yet in playne and open tearmes, euen bare faced, as it were, doe ſeeke to ſeduce vs, and to drawe vs to their falſe and ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latrous woorſhip and ſervice in Poperie, as namelie by their Maſſe, Mattens, Enſong, Purification, and other ſuch like:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:6302:7"/>Whereas you much more dangerouſly and euen vnder a maske or viſard as it were, and not vnlike to him that transformeth him ſelfe into an Angell of light, doe goe about to drawe and allure vs to the ſelfe ſame falfe worſhip &amp; ſervice but by clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier names and honeſter titles, as to their <hi>Purification</hi> by the title and name of Thankeſgiving, that is, to a Iewiſh Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie that ſhould be aboliſhed, vnder the pretence &amp; colour of a ſeruice of God that ſhould be continued.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But I pray you Couſen Puritane, is there no difference betwixt that in Poperie and ours?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>The difference (as I haue bene tolde by learned men) is onely in this, That theirs is in Latin &amp; yours in Englisſh, otherwiſe your proper Thankeſgiuing which yee call Churching, is even the very ſame woord for woord (excepting only the Title, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in (as I ſaye) yee iuggle and walke a little more covertly then they) with their Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication in Poperie. And can the changing
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:6302:7"/>of a name or title alter the thing it ſelfe or make it of another nature? If yee haue that gift and power amongst you, then yee may as well bring vs in the Maſſe vnder the name and title of a Communion: and ſo he that refuſeth to goe to Maſſe, you may ſerue him with a Citatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for not comming to the Communion, as in the like caſe you doe now by vs, you trouble vs and call vs in queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for denying of Thankeſgiuing, becauſe we refuſe to be Purified.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In good faith it is more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue conſidered of, whether that in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perie be ſo neare agreeing to ours as you ſpeak of, I beleeue your leaders haue miſ-informed you. But how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer it be and howſoeuer the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtes doe holde and account of it, it makes no great matter. The Church you ſee now holdeth it for no other then a meere</hi> Thankeſgiuing, <hi>which is very deeent and requiſite for euerie woman after ſo great deliuerance.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>What if the Church ſhould holde our
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:6302:8"/>Ladies Pſalter to be Davids Pſalter, or t'h Aue Marie for a Prayer? Should I therefore take and vſe th'one for Davids Pſalter, and th'other for a Prayer? I know the Lord is to be thanked for all his mercies, much more for ſo great a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing as Childbirth is: But as we are to giue God thankes, and are therevnto tyed and bound in duetie and allegeance: ſo are we ſtill to doe the ſame according to the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of him that commaundeth, and after the ſquare and rule of his ordinance, and not after the preceptes, phanſies and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions of men, eſpeciallie after the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of the man of Synne, that is after the manner of the ſuperstitious and idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous Papiſtes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But in faith doe you not thinke it a decent thing, that after ſo great an eſcape, and for the birth of a babe into the worlde, there ſhould bee Thankſgiving? or would you haue no differeuce betwixt reaſonable creatures and beaſtes, but that it
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:6302:8"/>ſhould bee left indifferent to vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rulie men to accompanie with their wives at their pleaſures, without re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of their weaknes and vnclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>You aske me wonderfull ſtrange things: Firſt whether it be not a decent thing v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon ſuch a deliuerance and the birth of a Babe into the worlde, there ſhould not bee Thankefgiving. Secondlie, whether it ſhould bee left indifferent for men to playe the beaſtes with their wives. Vnto which I aunſwere, that the manner of Churching that you thus trouble vs for, doeth not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe anie of theſe inconveniences: There being in it in trueth no maner of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving at all, but onelie a ſpeach or ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcription of a Thankeſgiving. Socondlie, whereas by the law of God, to touch a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in the time of her ſeparation and vncleaneſſe, ſhould bee death, what pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment haue you prouided for this ſo great and haynous enormitie? Or howe doeth your Churching of women reſtraine
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:6302:9"/>a carnall and licentious appetite from exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting his villenous and beaſtlie deſire? Hath he not his full ſwindge and libertie to doe what he lift for all that? So that yee complaine of dangers, diſorders, &amp; incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veniences, and yet leaue them ſtill as you found them without cure or redreſſe, neuer caring for anie thing ſo your ydle Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie may be kept.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>A man may eaſelie ſmell (gentle Couſen) where you haue bene at ſchoole, yet I haue talked in my daies with ſome of your own crew, and they hau cheld it for a thing in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different at the leaſt, and haue not bene halfe ſo hotte in it as you, and therefore for the loue I beare you, I would wiſhe you to haue ſome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of modeſtie and womanhood. For yea faith when you haue ſaide and wrangled all that you can, it will be found a moſt decent thing.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>A decent thing? What talke you of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie? I tell you I hold it fer more then a
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:6302:9"/>Decent thing, even for a religious thing, and a part of my bounden duetie, if it bee (as you ſay) a Thankeſgiving and a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God. But I pray you tell me, becauſe you wiſh me to haue a regard of modestie and womanhood, haue you had any infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of any miſ behaviour againſt me, either in my ſpeach, company, or cariage of my ſelfe, if you haue, I ſhall thanke you as my good kinſman to admoniſh me of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>By my trouth no: if it were not for this odde pieviſhneſſe of yours, (whereby you trouble both your ſelfe and your friendes more then needs) I doe not (ſo God helpe me) knowe or heare any thinge by you that deſerveth reproofe: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I am the willinger to pull you out of it if I could.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>It were well indeed if a could be pulled from my faultes and you from your ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. But when you friend or kinſman doeth any thing or refrayneth from anie thing of conſcience (as I may ſafelie pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>test
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:6302:10"/>vnto you in this caſe I doe) Then the way and meanes to ſet me ſtraight (if I be awry) is as I take it, the ſacred Scripturs and woord of God, which if you bring, or any good reaſon out of it for proofe and warrant of this your Churching, woe and double woe to me if I ſubſcribe not to it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Whop: here is a revell and adoe with</hi> Scriptures, <hi>my kinſwoman, you ſay, refrayneth of</hi> Conſcience: <hi>But fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> what doeth ſhee refrayne? forſooth from Thankeſgiving to God: Is not this pretie ſtuffe, or is not this a warme Conſcience?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Not ſo: Deceyue not your ſelfe, nor tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph not before the victorie, your kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman thanketh God ſhe hath bene better taught then ſo. It is not from Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing to God (as you would haue it) that ſhe refrayneth of Conſcience, but onely from Iewiſh or Popiſh Purifying ſhadowed and varniſhed over with a colour or ſhewe of Thankeſgiving. Thus ſhee tolde you once before, and this ſhee telleth you againe and
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:6302:10"/>againe. But I pray you let me aske you one thing.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Is not Thankeſgiving a ſervice of God? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes: I hope no man doubtes of that.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>What meane you then to harpe ſo much vpon Decencie and modestie? Would you haue vs ſerue God for Dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie? Sometimes againe you ſaye that Churching is a thing indifferent, a trifle, and a matter of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, and yet you will needes haue it to he a Thankeſgiving to God. Howe can this hang togeather then, that one &amp; the ſame thing ſhould be a matter of Dece<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cie, of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differencie, or a trifle of no moment, &amp; yet a ſeruice of God? Is the ſeruice of God come to that paſſe amongst you now?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I meane onely the Ceremonie of it, as the Tyme, and th'Attyre, the companie of women, the offerings, and the feaſting of neighbours and friendes, to be as thinges indifferent &amp; of no moment: But not the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:6302:11"/>and thankſgiuing in the church, that I holde to bee holy and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>The trueth is yee holde yee can not tell what amongst you: The Ceremonie ſtickes ſo neare to your ſeruice, and your maner of ſeruice is ſo ſutable and agreeing with your Ceremonie, that yee can not for your liues ſever the one from th'other. Take away the Ceremonie, and there is no need of your ſeruice that I ſee. Therefore you may doe well in my conceite, to let them both hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forward ſleepe and ſurceaſe. For lett the poore woman that hath eſcaped, bee never ſo thankfull, or let her huſband (as mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter of the familie) with his ſervantes and friends giue God thankes never ſo earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie and Chriſtianlie for that deliverance, (and that euen then when the remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of that mercie of God is freaſheſt in their memories) yet all this is nothinge to you, nor of no reckoning, vnleſſe the Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man may haue her ſolemne Purification at her monethes end, with her white vayle
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:6302:11"/>or ſome ſuch marke to be knowen by, which is a manifest ſigne that albeit yee pretende Thankeſgiuing, yet in trueth yee care not for it, ſo your Popiſh cuſtome and ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of Purifying be not broken of.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Indeed it were fitt that ye women ſhould appoint the ſervice and cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Church, and then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like we ſhould be wel &amp; handſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie ſerved. But I pray you tel me one thing: What if for the peace of the Church you ſhould giue thankes af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter this maner as in the book is pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed, what diſcredite, daunger or inconvenience would enſue to you vpon that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>That is as much to ſay in good Engliſh, as what if for the peace of the Church one ſhould make ſhew to giue thankes, when in deed and in trueth there is no Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at all? were not that a plaine mock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of God, a kinde of Hypocriſie, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaning of the name &amp; Religion of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Truſt me I thinke you are one of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:6302:12"/>the perverſeſt creatures that ever a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie man dealt with. I ſpeake not one woord of a ſhew of Thankeſgiving, but of giving thankes in deede, and looke now whither you be runne.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why did you not ſpeake of giving thanks after the maner as the Booke preſcribeth: and that as I haue often tolde you, is but a ſhew or ſhadow and no trueth. How am I perverſe then, when I ground vppon your owne ſpeaches? Now becauſe you aske me what inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>venience would enſue if I ſhould for anie reſpect vſe this prete<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded Than kſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giving, I will ſhew you (if you will giue me leaue, &amp; that you will with patience heare me) how I ſhall therein offende many and ſundrie wayes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>As how I pray you for my lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Two wayes I haue alreadie told you of: as first that in ſo doeing, I ſhould therein ſhewe my ſelfe either Iewish or Popish.</p>
               <p>Secondlie, that in fayning to giue GOD thankes, and to vſe no one woord tending
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:6302:12"/>to that ende, nor looking that way, is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing els but in a ſort to mocke God to his face.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well what then?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Thirdlie in ſo doeing, I ſhall not onely nouriſh, foster and maintayne manie ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perstitious and erroneous opinions in the heartes of th'ignorant, and ſo ſtrengthen the ſimple in their falſe woorſhip, but alſo fall into divers and ſundrie moſt daunge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous abſurdities: as namelie, firſt of all that a woman after childbirth is vncleane and vnholy, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary to th'Apoſtles wordes, who teacheth vs that a Woman is ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by bearing of children. For what may Purifying I pray you preſuppoſe, but ſome former vncleanneſſe? Likewiſe, that a woman is helde for the time as an excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate perſon, and therefore moſt ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemnly be receyued agayn into the church. For what may Churching preſuppoſe but ſome former excluding, ſhutting out and cutting off?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Theſe then I perceyue are ſome
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:6302:13"/>of your ſuppoſed abſurdities, haue you any more of them?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well iest as you pleaſe, I haue more of them then you or any man of your place ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with anie conſcience anſwere or avoyde.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Let vs heare them the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I pray you, and diſpatch that we may know all our payne at once.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why then I ſay further that in yeelding to this Churchinge of yours, I ſhould by myne example condemne the primitiue Church, and all the reformed Churches in other Countreyes at this day, who vſe no ſuch churchings: and withall iuſtifie and approoue the papiſts, and all other ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious churches that ioine with them in the vſe of it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>A great piece of woorke, as if it were ſuch a matter to varie and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent a little from Calvin or Beza, I tell you they may as well learne of vs, as we of them.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Who ſpake of Calvin or Beza? I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe you I did not ſo much as think of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:6302:13"/>I ſpake onely of the Primitiue and Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med churches. And albeit thoſe men you ſpeak of were worthie inſtruments in Gods church, &amp; ſuch as we haue cauſe to thank God for: yet the Lord I know might haue ſpread foorth the light of his Goſpell, and reformed his Church, had they neuer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But this is the manner of you all, you broode of Chauncelors &amp; your Aſſociates, when you can ſaye nothing, then you fall ſtraight a girding &amp; railing on Calvin or Beza, or ſome ſuch worthie man.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Gentle Couſen, be not angrie, I meane you no hurt yea faith. What other inconveniences or abſurdities doe you finde in this Churchinge, ſpeake your minde freelie, for I am even bent to heare you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I ſhould therein either my ſelf abuſe, or yeeld to th' abuſing of the woord of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſo I pray you?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I meane concerning the Pſalme that is there appointed for that purpoſe, vz. the <hi>121</hi> Pſalme, which being left to the chuch
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:6302:14"/>by the holy Ghost for comfort and conſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in time of distreſſe, to applie it to Thankeſgiving, contrarie to the purpoſe and meaning of the holy Ghost, must needes (as I ſay) be a playne abuſing and prophaning of the woord. And of it bee well conſidered of, it will be founde to bee more fitte a great deale for a woman in the time of her travel, agonie &amp; diſtreſſe, then afterward when ſhe is of ſtrength &amp; in good estate.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yea faith yea faith goſſippe, I doubt not if any of your preciſe crew had ſett down that Pſalme for that purpoſe, but you would haue liked of it well enough for all the cavills and quarrells you make a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it now.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Thinke you ſo S<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: Well I ſee that men of your occupation may eaſilie bee decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. But to deale plainlie and not to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble with you, one eſpeciall reaſon a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong others that draweth mee to diſlike and refuſe this Iuel of yours (I meane your
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:6302:14"/>Churching) is, that in yeelding therevn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, I ſhould iustifie you and your fellowes in your crooked and vnconſcionable pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, that is in vrging and preſsing your owne Traditions before the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundements of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And bee theſe the pretie reaſons that mooue you thus to diſlike the cuſtome and reverent vſage of our Church? Now ſurely it ſheweth the waywardnes of your conceyte, in that you preferre your owne will before the peace of the Church, which ought to be dearer vnto you then thus to ſtand out &amp; endaunger your ſelfe about ſuch trifles, &amp; mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of nothing, that are not woorth a ruſh to ſpeake of.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>No are? Then I ſay ſtill, The more ſhame for you to keepe ſuch a revell and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doe, for ſuch things as your ſelfe confeſſe are not woorth whisteling: and therin you ſhew your ſelues to bee right Scribes and Phariſees, that is, Hypocrites, tithing
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:6302:15"/>mint and cumine, and leaving iudgment and mercy, troubling the children of God and thoſe that ye ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not tuftlie charge with anie crime, for not obſeruing your Tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions &amp; beggerly Ceremonies, as Croſsing, Kneeling, Churching, &amp;c. and in the meane ſeaſon ſuffring the breakers of Gods holy commandements (aske Miſtres A. B. els, &amp; a nombre of knowne Papiſtes, Athe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſtes, Charmers, Blaſphemers, Prophaners of the Saboth, and ſuch like) to goe ſcotfree and vnpuniſhed, as if your whole delight, careand watchfulneſſe were only for th'ob ſeruation of theſe bables and fruitleſſe Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonies of yours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O M<hi rend="sup">rs</hi>
                  </hi> A. B. <hi>I perceiue is a great more in your eye, wel I pray God that you of the holy brotherhood that make it ſo daintie, do (the beſt of you) liue no worſe then ſhe doeth now, what ſoever ſhe hath bene heretofore.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Amen ſay I, and better to. Indeed to doe her no wrong as I heare no great exclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her, for any notorious crime, ſo on
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:6302:15"/>th'other ſide, wee that are her neighbours, may ſafely acquite her of any great co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation that ſhee hath for any holy and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious courſe thereby to draw on others by her example. Therfore praiſe her as much as you list, when you haue done the beſt you can, ſhee will bee founde but an ordinarie woman: and the ſpecial thing that you can co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mend in her (for any thing I ſee) is this: that ſhe is as quietly chuchedwhe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> her time comes, as any of the reſt of her neighbours.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I would to God I could ſay ſo by you to Couſen, condition I had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen twentie pound yea faith, &amp; then you might haue eaſed vs of much of this trouble.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>You may doe one day, when you ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> bring me any ſufficient reaſon and warrant for it out of the Scripture. And if you will but giue vs a tolleration and diſpenſation for it till then, we will aske no more.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſay well, I know your mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. But in good truth I muze that the Peace of the Church doeth no more mooue you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:6302:16"/>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>You muze you ſay, that the peace of the Church doeth uo more mooue me: And I muze likewiſe what you would haue ſaide if you had lived in the dayes of our Savi. Chriſt, who defended his Diſciples againſt the Phariſees in a verier trifle &amp; of farre leſſe moment then this our refuſall of your Churching.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Where I pray you, ſhew me that for my learning.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>What ſay you to the refuſall of waſhing of handes at meate? Is not that as ſmall a matter as may be? And if you had bene by at that time, when our Savior ſo boldly defended his Diſciples therein, it is like e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough you would haue coumpted him for a verie Trifler, or ſome buſie Troubler of the Peace of the Church, that would keepe ſuch a doe for nothing. Sure by your dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling with vs we can coniecture none other.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tuſh the Compariſons are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Trulie even as like as may be. The Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees founde fault with the Diſciples for
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:6302:16"/>breaking a Tradition of th' Elders, viz. waſhing of handes at meate: and you find fault with vs for breaking a much woorſe Traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of yours. You aske vs often whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Churching be not a Decent thing: We aske you againe, whether waſhing bee not both a Decent thing, a cleanly thing, and a wholeſome thing? Our Savior (you ſee) defended his Diſciples in the breach of that Decencie of thoſe Phariſees of that age: and his woord doth warrant and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fende vs in the breach of this ſuppoſed De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie of your Phariſſes of this age.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nay then yea faith, if yee goe to that, ye may take your ſelues by the noſe Miſtres Couſen: For who the Devill be the right Phariſſes &amp; Hy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocrites if yee be not? Ye are ſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mure, and ye make it ſo nice and ſo holy amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gſt you, that by the Maſſe a dogge would not dwell with you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I perceyue if a dogge dwelt with you, if you could but make him ſpeake once, you would quicklie teach him to ſweare.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:6302:17"/>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O that is all your grace amongſt you: you thinke your ſelues ſo pure over other men, becauſe you can a litle bridle your ſelues from ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and yet ye wil doe tenne times woorſe and make no bones at it. As couetous, as ſpitefull, and malicious yee are the moſt of you, as dogges. I knowe one of your crew who would not ſweare for no good, and vſed ordinarilie to pray with his me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his chamber, and yet beeing at a Knights houſe, where hee had good entertayneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, they prayed ſo har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilie amongſt them, that for conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſake they faire thwited me of a valence of a bedde, and caried that &amp; a piece of plate with them to the value of twentie nobles at the leaſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well though this peradventure may be one of your legend ſtories, for any thing I know, yet alow it to be true, what gette you by that? one ſinne you know excuſeth not another. Theſe were hypocrites &amp; theeves,
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:6302:17"/>therefore you to avoide this daunger, will needes be ſwearers &amp; ruffeans: what phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſike or policie call you that to avoid Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie by plaine and open iniquitie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why I doe not defend ſwearing to bee good, woman: you doe not heare me ſay ſo, I wiſh I could leaue it with all my heart: It is but a foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh cuſtome and comes from me at vnawares, and that many times whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I thinke no harme in the world.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Th'Apostle is against you in that: for he ſayeth, Out of the aboundance of the heart the mouth ſpeaketh: And our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our ſaieth, That out of the heart comes e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill thoughts, and yet you can droppe vile oathes amongst you (ſuch is your skill) &amp; thinke no harme. I muſt needes commend you for this, by meanes whereof you haue brought one notable thing to paſſe in our Church, and I wiſh for my part yee were Chronicled for it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What is that good goſſipper</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why, That albeit there be many Pari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:6302:18"/>amongeſt vs without a preaching Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister, yet to mende the matter, there bee few Dioces in the lande without a ſwea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Chauncelor.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>That is more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you know, good huſwife. But if it were ſo, I doe not thinke but the woorſt Chauncelor amongſt vs doeth more good then many of your vpſtart and buſie hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Preachers, pratlers I ſhould ſay.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well, to let that rest as it is (for if there by any thing amiſſe, wee ſhould doe wrong to looke for amendes from you) you ſee evidentlie, that th'example which I alleadged of our Saviour Christ in repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Phariſees and defendinge his Diſciples in their refuſall of that trifle of waſhing of handes, is both a check to you, for thus troubling of vs without cauſe, &amp; a good warrant for vs to doe as we doe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Doe I ſee it? I promiſe you I muſt gette me better ſpectacles then, then ever I could yet light on.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well, if you doe not ſee it, I muſt needes
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:6302:18"/>holde with you, that your ſpectacles are ſtarke naught in deede: But whether you doe ſee it, or will not ſee it, it is and ought to be a leſſon of instruction to vs whom you now thus trouble: That whenſoeuer anie Phariſaicall hypocrites doe ſtrictlie vrge and preſſe the keeping of their owne traditions (bee they neuer ſo ſmall and trifling) with the neglect of the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of God, then it is our partes by all lawfull &amp; body meanes to bende our ſelues against them, and not to yeelde to th'ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation of the least of them: much leſſe when the Traditions ſhalbe noiſome, hurt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and ſuperstitious, and derogatorie to the glorie of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In good faith it was neuer merrie world ſince theſe twatling women became divines. I ſee I do but ſpend time with you. And yet when you haue ſayd and done all that you can for your life, it will be founde (as I haue ſaid) but a trifle that you ſtand vppon, whereas the peace of the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:6302:19"/>Church is, or ought to bee to you a matter of great moment, and a thing that you ought daily to pray for, if you haue (as you pretend) any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience with you, or regard of bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therlie loue, with a defire to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine vnitie, and to avoyde iarres &amp; diſſentions.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>We are I confeſſe to pray for the peace of Syon: For they ſhall proſper that loue her. But what? Is the Church now become a maynteiner of trifles? By your ſpeaches ſo often iterated and redoubled (for you harpe ſtill on that ſtring) it ſhould bee ſo: and what indignitie were that? But in deede as I haue told you the thing we ſtand vpon (if it be rightlie examined) is not in that nature of indifferencie as you would beare the world in hande it is, make of it what you will either Thankeſgiving or Purifying if it be Thankeſgiving indeed, it is my bounden duetie (ſay I) to performe it, and a ſinne to leaue it vndone: If it bee Purifying, it is my bounden duetie to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:6302:19"/>it, and a ſinne to practiſe it, becauſe it treadeth vnder foote the ſufficiencie of of the death and bloudſheading of IESVS Christ, which is th'onlie purgation of my ſinne. So that turne it which way you will, it is no light matter or trifle of ſmall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garde, as you would haue it, but a thinge that one way or other greatly concerneth the glorie of God, &amp; therein alſo you ſeeme to me apparantlie to croſſe, entangle &amp; en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſnare your ſelfe in your owne ſpeaches.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſo I pray you?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I haue tolde you alreadie, and that ſo often, that I am halfe wearie of telling it. But ſure your minde is ſo on your haulfpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, that you neither remember what I ſay, nor thinke on that you ſay your ſelfe. Haue you not alwayes called this Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of yours, a Thankeſgiving? and haue you not laboured by the title of it in the Booke, to defende it to be a Thankeſgiuing and no Purifying?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yes that I haue, and ſo I ſay ſtill.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why then I ſaye for ſhame away with
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:6302:20"/>this trifle and trifling of yours, and let vs heare no more of that: For Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving you know must needes be a part of Gods woorſhip and ſeruice. And what an impious &amp; vngodly thing were it to make the holy woorſhip and ſeruice of God a tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fle, a matter of nothing, not worth a ruſh, or a thing to bee done or not done at our pleaſures? I protest vnto you, if it were a Thankeſgiving in deede, that is ſuch a part of Gods woorſhip as he hath comaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and preſcribed in his word, if I ſhould wilfully refuſe to doe it, I were not woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie to bee coumpted a member of his Church.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet ſtill me thinkes the peace of the Church doeth not poize and prevaile with you as it ſhould doe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Heere is a doe with the <hi>Peace of the Church,</hi> and yet when ye haue all done, a man may eaſilie ſee that though ye talke of it never ſo much, yee vſe it for the most part but as a ſtaulking horſe amongſt you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What meane you by that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:6302:20"/>
               <p>Why, you know well enough, that the ſtaulkinge horſe is not to blame for the death of the foule, he doeth but onely ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe and ſtand before the fouler while hee killeth him: Even ſo doe you. The Peace of the Church (as you handle it) is a nota<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble vaile to ſhadowe all your deformities and corruptions. If a good Minister doe not yeelde to your lawleſſe and vnconſcio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable ſubſcription, or if he over skippe the Croſſe in Baptiſme, Ring in Mariage, or any ſuch needles Ceremonie, then ſtraight you choke him with the peace of the Church, the peace of the Church, and ſo you doe now by vs for our refuſall of knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Churching.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I pray you in good earneſt, why may not theſe and more then theſe be endured and yeelded vnto for the peace of the Church?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>If the Peace of the Church were ſo deare vnto you as you pretende and make ſhew of, then would ye never for ſhame trouble either Ministers or people for ſuch odde
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:6302:21"/>things as thoſe that rather hinder then further men in Religion. But your maner is whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſpeake of one thing to meane an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. You ſpeake of the Peace of the Church, but you meane ſtill the peace of your Hierarchie, the peace of your vnrulie places and offices, the Peace of all your Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſh &amp; beggerlie Ceremonies, ſo they may ſtande ſtill vntouched, if yee Chauncelyers and your Officials may be at quiet in your roomes and iuriſdictions: Litle (the Lord knowes) doe yee care for the peace of the Church: and that is ſeene not only by your troubling of vs now without cauſe, but by your ordinarie ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cing, ſuſpending &amp; im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſoning of the beſt and holieſt Preachers for theſe trifles, and your countenancing and allowing of dumme dogges, bee there liues and behaviour neuer ſo ſhamefull.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O (my good kinſwoman) we haue heard enough of theſe matters long agoe. Theſe ſuppoſed quarrells haue ben anſwered and anſwered againe, you come to late yea faith with
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:6302:21"/>your baſkett of Apples now. What a Devil ſhould you medle with any of theſe matters? It were much fitter for ſuch as you are, to medle with your ſpindle and your wheele, and ſoberlie to attend your trades &amp; vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations, then thus in the pride of your heartes to controlle your bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and to deale in Church cauſes which belong not vnto you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I was I thank God buſied in my vocatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and ſo I might haue ben ſtill, had not you ſommoned me the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce by your officer. I know right well Church cauſes belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g not to ſuch as I am to deale in, neither doe I meddle withall farther then by way of ſute or co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plainte to thoſe that haue authoritie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe. And if the Peace of the Church can not mooue you to leaue cyting &amp; troubling vs for trifles, whom otherwiſe you can not charge with anie crime, never blame vs if the bare ſound and noyſe of the Peace of the Church doe not at al mooue vs to yeeld to any of your trifling &amp; fruitles Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies against our conſciences.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:6302:22"/>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well I am ſorie you are ſo wilfull yea faith: I perceiue I ſhall doe no good of you.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I tell you you may eaſilie doe good of me, and eaſilie draw me to the bent of your bow, if you can produce and alleage vnto me but one only ſentence and proofe out of the ſcriptures of God.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Scripture? there is nothing with you but Scriptures. No No. It is even the pride of your heart, and pieviſh ſingularity of your owne conceyte that doth thus draw you. Why doe you thinke no body ſeeth anie thing but your ſelfe? or doe you thinke there be not as ſober &amp; as honeſt wome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as you Churched?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Then I perceyue you haue no Scripture in the worlde to perſwade mee with, your onely ſcripture is the pride of my heart, the Singularitie of my conceite, and I can not tell what. But you aske me whether as ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest women as I be not churehed? I aske you againe, Whether as honest men as you
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:6302:22"/>haue not denied Chriſt. Th'examples of the godlie (you know) are not to be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but in godlines, whereas it is the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon guiſe of you and your generation to make a ſolemne gathering and calling as it were of the ſcabbes, imperfections and bleamiſhes of the best men, and then to lay them in our diſh ſtraight as a choake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to vs: as for example, if ye find once that Father Latimer and Ridley, or anie ſuch like reverend man, did weare ſquare cappe and ſurplus, why then there is no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie but this must bee proclaymed ſtraight as an authenticall warrant to all the ſucceeding Miniſters of the lande, that they may boldlie and ſafelie yeelde to the wearing of the like attire.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>And I promiſe you, It is ſomthing I tell you as light as you make of it. Why is th'example of the godly Martyrs nothing with you, and your preciſe brotherhoode?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Yes it is ſomething: but I doe not thinke it ſhould waigh more with vs then th'ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:6302:23"/>of Abraham, David, or Peters whoſe ſteppes you know we must not follow when they ſlippe or goe awry. But will you your ſelues I pray you (if a man may aske it) ſtande to the iudgement, and bee ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by th'example of the godlie Martyrs?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>I ſee no reaſon but wee may and ought.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why then downe falles to the grounde ſtraight your lawleſſe oath of Inquiſition, wherewith yee ſo plague the Church now a dayes, Iudge by Mai. Tindall els, Mai. La<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart, and others that ſuffered for the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of Gods trueth.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Indeed Ma. Tindall and Ma. Lam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bart were ſomewhat wilfull.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Iust, how els? Thus yee marſhall the Martyrs as it pleaſe your ſelues, when they may ſerue your turne (be it in neuer ſo great ignorance and weakneſſe of theirs) then their names, their pietie, and their patience are layde before vs in great and capitall letters, as paternes to follow. But when they croſſe you in any thing (bee the
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:6302:23"/>ſame never ſo apparantlie warranted by the Scriptures) then alas, they were but men, yea and many times wilfull men, as you doe now moſt iniuriouſlie ſlaunder M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Lambart and M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Tindall.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>But to leaue theſe circumſtances and by matters, doe you thinke it is a ſinne to be Churched? ſpeak your conſcience.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>As I haue alreadie ſaied, if it be a ſinne to make ſhew of Thankeſgiving, and yet to giue no thankes at all: if it be a ſinne to abuſe and miſapplie the ſacred Scriptures of God to another ende and purpoſe then it was giuen by the holy Ghost: if it bee a ſinne to ſtrengthen and confirme the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pist in his ſuperstition, and the ſimple and ignorant in their falſe &amp; erroneous woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip: if all or any of theſe bee ſinnes, then doe I not ſee how your Churching (as it is vſed amongst you) can eſcape the ſtampe and brandmarke of ſinne. And howſoever it may bee to others, I doe well aſſure my ſelfe it were a ſinne and wickednes in mee,
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:6302:24"/>becauſe it is againſt the light of mine owne conſcience grounded vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the reaſons that I haue alleaged vnto you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, but if you like not the Pſalme in the Booke whiche you keepe ſuch adoe at, and be ſo coy &amp; conceyted, that for feare of abuſing it, forſooth you are loth to haue it read to you, yet your Miniſter may vſe another if he will, and pray as he thinkes good. So you would de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>centlie &amp; womanly come to church at your time, as other your neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours doe, by my trouth for my part I could bee content to winke at ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie things, and ſhew you any favour I could.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Then I perceyue you haue forgotten how in the beginning when I asked you what you meant by Churching, you tolde mee that which was preſcribed in the booke: For law ſayed you, would not warrant any other. And are you come now to giue vs libertie to vſe another, ſo we would quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:6302:24"/>obſerue your Ceremonie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>You ſay well, Is this the thankes I haue for my kindneſſe and favor to you, in that I am contented to ſaue you from trouble and daunger, to yeeld a litle to your weakneſſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe you ſeeme to make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſcience of I can not tell what? In good faith goſhip, you ſhall fitt till your heeles ake before I offer you this favour a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Nay but for all your chafing, I would not haue you mistake me: What favour ſo euer you ſhew me, I will not by Gods grace be vnthankfull for it to my power. But I vnderſtood you that you gaue me euen now free libertie to ſpeake my minde, and that you would willinglie heare what ſoeuer I ſhould ſay: and I tooke it and doe ſtill take it, that your Sommoning and ſending for me hither, was rather in your loue to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferre with me and to ſatisfie me, then by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie rigour of your law to puniſh me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>By my trouth you hitte it right:
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:6302:25"/>For I was greatlie beholden to your Father, and therefore I haue reaſon to wiſhe you well, &amp; in that reſpect I would gladlie doe you what good I may.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why, then you continew this minde to giue me your free warrant to ſpeake in this caſe what I thinke, and to cast all the doubtes and make all th'obiections I can againſt you, that ſo you may the better re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolue me in th'end?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How els? In the name of God, ſpeake you minde boldlie, neither ſhall you offend me with any thing you ſay: For I imagine you can ſay nothing in this cauſe, but I haue heard it alreadie.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well then, doeth not this (I pray you) plainlie verifie and confirme that which I told you of before when I likened you to the Phariſeis, vz. That your own fooliſh Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions and fruitleſſe Ceremonies were dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer to you and of more pretious accoumpt, then the Sacred ordinance of God?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:6302:25"/>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How ſo, I conceyue not that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>No? Did not you ſay that for my ſake you would be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent to winck at the breach of the Booke, and giue the Minister leaue to vſe other prayers, ſo I would be content in any ſort to be Churched, and keepe your monethlie and manerlie Ceremonie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why if I ſaied ſo, you are the more beholden to me for that I doe not meane (I tell you) to ſhew euery bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die that favour.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well, howſoeuer I may in this regarde thanke you for your loue to me, yet to deale plainelie with you, I can not therein praiſe you for your loue to the Church, nor never ſhall till I ſee Preaching as much beholden to you as Churching is.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, doe you thinke I doe not preferre the preaching of the worde before anie other ceremonie of the Church, be it neuer ſo commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>It ſhould appeare no by your dealinge with our Miniſter. </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:6302:26"/>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Your Miniſter! yea faith your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter hath no more witte then hee occupies: He knowes not who is his friend nor who is his foe. I would to God he would be his owne friende once. Stand ſticking and mincing it at theſe bables and trifles as he doth, when he might be quiet in his mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterie, if he would him ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>So might wee poore women (whom you thus trouble) be quiet too if we would bee Churched: Our Minister you know is an honest man of life, and a painfull Teacher in his place, you can not charge him with anie miſdemeanour for your life. He prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth amongest vs with great fruite, and hath wonne manie to the Goſpell, and yet for refuſall of your lawleſſe ſubſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide the Statute, and for not wearing of your ſurplus, &amp; not Croſsing in Baptiſme, you neuer let him rest among you, but one while you are doeing with him in your Court: an other while the Purſevant from the High Commiſsion trounceth him: So
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:6302:26"/>that yee make the poore man ſpend the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter part of his poore living in iaunceling up and down about the moon ſhine in the Town-dich.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, who is this long of, gentle Couſen? Is not all this long of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? There be as wiſe &amp; as learned as he that yeeld to all this you ſpeake of, and more then this for the peace of the Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>But I pray you tell mee, Why may you not be as kinde to him in his Miniſterie &amp; Preaching, as you offer to bee to me in this Ceremonie of Churching? You ſaye you preferre the preaching of the Goſpell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore anie ceremonie whatſoever: if you meane in deede as you ſay, then for Gods ſake wincke a little at the breach of the Booke in him as well as you are contented to doc in me: let not your loue to me in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate bee greater then your loue to the Church in publike. Looke a litle thorough your fingers, and paſſe by as if you ſaw not his refuſall of the Croſſe and Surplus.
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:6302:27"/>That ſo we may enioye the meanes of our ſalvation in peace. And if in anie caſe you will yeelde to the breach of the Booke, let it bee for the Goſpell ſake, and not for a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>remonie.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In good faith, I can not tell what to ſay to you, with beeing among the perverſe, you haue gotten as it were a kinde of habite of perverſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. I had rather then any golde your huſband and you had neuer planted your ſelues in that Pariſh: why you were well enough before, and well accoumpted of among your neighbours, and it muſt needs grieue many of your good friendes to ſee you in theſe tunes now.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Moman.</speaker>
               <p>I may truelie thanke God, as for many other his mercies, ſo eſpecially for this that ever I came to this mans Miniſtery (whoms yee ſo trouble amongest you). I was indeed a Protestant before, and thought well of myſelfe, and yet (if I ſhall not lie to you) I had no more Religion then my horſe. But
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:6302:27"/>now I may truly ſay, that as my knowledge is in ſome meaſure increaſed, ſo I neuer made conſcience of ſinning and offending God, till I came to the place where I nowe dwell. All which as I muſt and doe attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to God, as th' Author and Founteine, ſo to our Minister as the meanes and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Indeede you haue made a very woorthie increaſe, and mended the matter wonderous wel. And all this is for nothing els but becauſe you are come from Churching to No Churching: what a wonderful cure and charge your Miniſter hath wrought in you. I beleeue he vſeth to Catechize you in nothing els but only in Churching, you ſeeme to be perfect in the point.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well, I would you could tell how to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge a good conſcience in your places, (any of you Chancelours) aſwell as our Miniſter doeth in his. His ordinarie tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching is (thankes be to God) in matters of
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:6302:28"/>more moment then you ſpeake of, and if you heard him once your ſelfe, I make no queſtion but you would ſay ſo. For mine owne part I never hearde him ſpeake pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blikly of this particular cuſtome of church<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ing in my life, further then might bee ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of any generall doctrine of his. Indeed I confeſſe I haue had private con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference with him about it, and hee hath fullie ſatisfied me.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>In what ſort (I pray you) hath he fatisfied you? may I be bold as to craue a copie, or to be pertaker with you of your ghoſtly fathers reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why you haue heard the moſt of them alreadie, and I haue made knowne to you at large the reaſons that haue mooued mee to ſhake off and abandon this fooliſhe and ſuperſtitious cuſtome of yours, wherewith I had well hoped you had bene ſatisfied.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Indeede you haue told me many prety things, but yet they bee ſuch as I haue hearde of before. Why,
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:6302:28"/>they be the common reaſons of you all amongſt you. I neuer had any of you before me, but they haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded euen as you doe, or to the ſame effecte.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>The more ſaye I (vnder correction) haue you to aunſwere for, That havinge had ſo manifest reaſons layed before you ſo long agoe, and the ſame ſo often iterated and repeated vnto you, there is yet no ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of relenting in you, but you doe ſtill perſist and goe on in your courſe, in trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling poore women without cauſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why you know my Lord Buſhop went farther with ſome of you not farre from your quarters, and made the proudeſt of them crouch, and come on their knees, enforcing the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to be Churched in deſpite of them, and that two or three yeares after they were layed. You would thinke I deale hardlie with you, if I ſhould vſe any of you ſo.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Now ſure it was Buſhoplike done of
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:6302:29"/>him if he did ſo. But what warrant I pray you had my Lord to make them crouch in this maner as you ſpeake of? Doeth the Booke or any Law of the lande authorize him to Church a woman <hi>3</hi> yeare after ſhee is brought to bedde? ſhew me that I pray you for my learning?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, you haue nothing to doe with that. Therefore it ſhall be good for you Couſen (as I haue told you) to medle with your own matters &amp; to bee armed howe to aunſwere for your ſelfe, and not to deale in things impertinent to your place.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Content then, you giue me good counſell: But remember your ſelf, I pray you, that it was you that brought in the Buſhop &amp; not I. I medled not with him till you ſpake of him. But to deſire to bee reſolved in ſome things of you is not I hope impertinent to my place, is it?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>No, god forbid, whatſoever you de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to be ſatisfied in, be bold I pray you to propound it, and I will thank
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:6302:29"/>you and doe my beſt to reſolue you as farre foorth as lieth in me.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why then in this Thankeſgiving you ſpeake of, who is it that you would haue giue thankes?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, the woman that hath bene deliuered.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>When is it that you would haue her giue God thankes? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>When ſhee is ſtrong and able to goe to Church.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>And not before? would you haue her for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gett her ſelf, and be vnthankfull till then?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nay, God forbid, I hope ſhee hath more grace then ſo. But I ſpeake of publike tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kſgiving &amp; not of private.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why, but the bleſsing you ſee is private, and what reaſon is it then, or what war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, or what example haue you out of the Scripture, that there ſhould be an ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſett ſeruice in Publike for euery priuate and perticular bleſsing? I would faine you reſolved me in that. If the Minister bee in duetie bounde to giue God thankes
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:6302:30"/>for euery private and particular bleſhing, why not then as well for my huſbands fall of his horſe, as for my deliverance? I tell you I holde my huſbande a farre more woorthy member of the Church then my ſelfe, and therefore I ſee no reaſon why yee ſhould not cauſe him to bee Churched as well as me, and ſo all others in our pariſhe that haue eſcaped either drowning or dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger of death.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Me thinkes Couſen you doe not rightly conſider of it as you ſhould doe. It is in my vnderſtanding ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther maner of thing then you take it for. There is you muſt marke in the thing a double bleſſing: The birth of a babe into the world bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an excellent creature of God: And the deliuerance and dangerous eſcape of the woman. No queſtion but the Church in this her ſeruice, hath a ſpeciall reference and relati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to both: In which regard it may well be called more then a private
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:6302:30"/>or particuler bleſſing?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Something you haue ſaied to the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and yet when it is examined it will bee founde nothing. A double bleſsing you call it: The birth of the babe, and the deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of the woman. But I ſay the Church in that ſet ſervice of hers hath no manner of reſpecte at all to the former of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is the birth of the childe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>How proove you that:</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>By the very practiſe of our Church whereof your ſelfe may bee a witneſſe. For if the woman die before her moneth, there is no maner of ſeruice nor Thankeſgiuing at all for the Babe, though it thriue and proſper neuer ſo much. Therefore the Church in thoſe her churching prayers, neuer regardeth that at all, having pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and giuen God thankes for the Babe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore at Baptiſme.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well what of all that?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why then you must giue mee leaue to holde my former opinion, That for the Church to establiſh a Publike ſeruice for
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:6302:31"/>euery private and ordinarie bleſsing (as Child-birth is) is without ground or war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant. Indeed I confeſſe that if the Queene or Princeſſe of a lande, in whom the whole Realme hath an intereſt, were deliuered of a Babe, then I take it the Church had ſome reaſons to make a Publike and generall Churching or Thankeſgiuing to God: As I haue heard that for the birth of King Edward there was: But otherwiſe ſuch an ordinarie ſeruice as yours is, for euery pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate woman ſuch as my ſelf, hath in mine opinion neither legges nor foundation to ſtande on.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O I remember now theſe were ſome of the woorthy reaſons that your Miniſter alleaged when hee was before me in Miſtres Winters caſe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>But what thinke you? Were they not ſound reaſons? or are you able by any co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour of reaſon to anſwere or avoid them?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, by your leaue, your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter (as holy as he is) plaied the Aſſe
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:6302:31"/>there egregiouſly.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>How ſo I pray you? Wherein? I premiſe you I ſee not but hee did that which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth to him in all faithfulneſſe.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why is not ſhee his patroneſſe I pray you, and did not her huſband giue him the benefice?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>What of that? </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why then you muſt needes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe he dealt but badly with her, &amp; vnkindly to refuſe to Church her.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I ſee no vnkindneſſe in it in the world nor yet any vndutifulneſſe to her, conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring at what an vnconvenient time ſhee ſent for him, on the Saboth day morning, and that in all post hast, of purpoſe as it is thought, to pike a quarrell to him, having conceyved a bitter diſpleaſure againſt him for his Sermon before.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Alas the gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> had thought (as ſhee ſaith) and had verely pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to haue gone to Church her ſelf ouer-night, but the weather fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling out ſomething whette and ſlab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bie
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:6302:32"/>in the morning, had it bene ſuch a matter for him to haue come downe to her when ſhee ſent for him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>What at that time and houre betwixt <hi>9</hi> and <hi>10</hi> of the clocke when he was readie to goe to the ſermon: Had that bene fitte thinke you?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sermon me no Sermons. By the maſſe I would not haue hazarded her diſpleaſure for that, knowinge that my living did depend vpon it. Why might hee not haue preached an other time, or haue fained ſome excuſe for that preſent, that hee had not ben well or ſo?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Nay like enough: This is euen like your ſelues, and fully ſutable to the rest of your proceedings. What other fruites ſhould one looke for from men of your constitution? But doeth not this iustifie that whiche I haue ſo often charged you with: That you more prize &amp; esteeme theſe bables of your owne hatching and invention, then the
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:6302:32"/>ſacred ordinance of God? And is it not a ſtrange witcherie, that ye can bee content amongst you thus to ſuffer the Preaching and Ministerie of the woord to giue place to a Iewiſh or Popiſh ceremonie?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O be not angrie good Couſen.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well, ye may ſee (if yee will not wilfullie blindfolde your ſelues) what miſchief and inconvenience comes by this ſo croſſe and perverſe dealing of yours. For what with the care of the Decencie of Churching and your careleſneſſe of the neceſsitie of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, ye haue almost marred all amongst you, and brought it ſo to paſſe, that the poore ignorant people of the lande doe thinke all the ſervice of GOD to lye in Churching, Croſsing, Kneeling, and bee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing houſeled (as they call it) at Easter. As for Preaching, they holde that for a ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous and needleſſe Ceremonie: and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when their ſeruice is done, they take it they may lawfullie goe out of the Church, though the Minister be readie to goe into the Pulpitt. And all this my good Couſen
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:6302:33"/>is long of you and your aſſociates. I must needs in all plaineſſe tell you what I thinke.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, theſe be things that you and I ſhall not redreſſe in haſt, gentle kinſwoman. We may well wiſh and pray for the redreſſe: but yea faith neither you nor al your preciſe bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therhood can for your liues tell how to helpe it.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>If we can not helpe it (as you ſay) yet it were to bad to go about to hinder it (as you doe) you ſpeake of praying and wiſſhing, &amp; yet I can not ſee that you do ſo much as wiſh and deſire the thing you ſpeake of: Nay it were well if yee did indeed wiſh a reformation and redreſſe from your heartes.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why, do you thinke mee ſo farre gone that I doe not wiſh well to the Church and State wherein I liue?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>It ſeemes no by your owne ſpeaches. For in your mouth you condemne the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter for that which in your conſcience you ought to commend him for. And what
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:6302:33"/>was the Ministers fault, I pray you? For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſooth he would not forſake and giue ouer his Preaching to Church his Patroneſſe, Wherevpon you ſweare, (Sermon you no ſermons) Yea and by your leaue, when the matter came before you (to your reproch be it ſpoken good Couſen, God forgiue you for it) you tooke part with the Gentlewo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man against our Minister. Call you this to wiſh well and to deſire and pray for re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation and amendement?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chanucelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Tuſh that was but in one particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar (woman) and for once only that I would haue had him ouerſkipt his ſermon for a future benefire both to the Church and him ſelf: and what hurt had it bene (I pray you) for him to haue layed aſide one ſermon, that afterward hee might haue preached manie ſermons in peace? As for my taking part with the Gentlewoman, that was for your Miniſters good, if you and he had eyes to ſee it: to the
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:6302:34"/>end that I might afterward th'eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier pacifie and preuaile with the Gentlewoma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, who I aſſure you was mightilie incenſed againſt him, and had in purpoſe to remooue him if ſhee could.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Well, if your purpoſe and intent were good, I am gladde of it, though God (you ſee) doe ſeldome bleſſe but rather croſſe &amp; curſe theſe purpoſes of yours, becauſe you walke not with a ſtraight foote and an vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right heart. But to lett that paſſe and to come to our former ſpeach of Thankeſgi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing, would you haue the Woman alone giue God thankes for that bleſsing, or her friendes to ioine with her therein?</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>What a queſtion is that? Is it not fitte and requiſite that her friendes that loue her, ſhould ioine with her in ſo good an action?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>How happens it then that ye handle the matter ſo amongeſt you in your manner of Churching, That neither the Huſbande
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:6302:34"/>must ioyne with his wife, nor the Father with his daughter, nor the Sonne with his Mother, nor the Brother with his Sister, nor they that are most bounde in nature and by the law of GOD to giue thankes, must not at all medle with it, nor haue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie thing to doe with all, as if they had no interest in that bleſsing at all, but were meere ſtraungers to it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chanucelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>O it is fitteſt in good faith that they onely that were by the woman in her anguiſh and trauell, ſhould be by her alſo at her Thankeſgiving. What a Devill ſhould men medle with womens matters?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>You ſay well, men must not medle with womens matters. But I alwayes tooke Thankeſgiuing to God to be a matter be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing to men as well as to women. And if men must not medle withall, what ſhould the Minister deale in it, or why ſhould he be troubled for not medling with this womans buſines? He was not by (you
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:6302:35"/>know, at the womans travell, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you might doe well to exempte him as well as you doe others: For you know when the Buſhop maketh and ordaineth a Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, be giueth him authoritie to Preach, to minister the Sacramentes, and to exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe Diſcipline, and not to Church women. This by th'institution is no part of his of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and therefore you may the rather par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don him if he happen to omitte it.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>He (you know) is the mouth of the Congregation. And who ſhould deale in the Prayers of the Church, but onely he?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>I confeſſe the Minister by his place &amp; function ought to be as well the mouth of God to the people to deliuer vs his will, as the mouth of the people to God to lay o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen our wantes and to craue his aſsiſtance. But in this caſe that you ſpeake of, of your ſolemne Churching, or rather Purifying of women, he is neither of both. Hee ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth ſhew (as I haue tolde you) of Thankſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giuing,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:6302:35"/>but giueth none in deede, in ſo much that your ſelues can not tell what to make of it for your liues, as a ſervice that is neither fiſhe nor fleaſh, nor good redde hearing: and yet yee must needes defende it and mainteyne it, and that ſtiffelie: yea and manie times make the Preachinge of the woord giue place vnto it, ſuch is your care of the peace of the Church. God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue it you my good Couſen. This is a trueth you know, I can not diſſemble with you.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well will you diſpatch, gentle Kinſwoman, and pay the Sumnor his fees, and ſo I am contented for this time to diſmiſſe you and your fellowes, till I ſend for you againe.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why doe you meane then in deede to trouble vs againe? I was in good hope ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther you had bene halfe wearie &amp; abaſhed of this that you haue done alreadie. Well, ſeeing you ſpeake of the Sumners fees, I must intreat you before you goe, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:6302:36"/>that good honeſt man of your owne making one Ma. Turne-peny.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Why ſhould I remember him?</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Becauſe he was once (you knowe) one of your graceleſſe Apparitors at Lichfield: And was dailie ſo buſilie occupied about his fees, and ſo earneſt to ſommon men for his vnlawfull gaine about ſuch like trifles, as you doe nowe trouble vs for, that you know what followed.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>By my trouth Couſen, it was no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſo badde as the worlde makes of it: Some matter there was, and ſome trouble of minde the poore man had toward his ende, But yea faith we ought to iudge the beſt.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>Why did not his maister (whom hee ſerved ſo devoutlie) ſommon him at his death to pay his fees? or did hee not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe at that time, that the Divell appea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red vnto him to bidde him diſpatch and make haste? And did hee not there-vpon end his dayes in great miſerie, to the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holders,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:6302:36"/>with fearfull cryes and ſchrikes of deſperation? I am ſure you will not denie this.</p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Chauncelor.</speaker>
               <p>
                  <hi>Well, well, The man you ſpeake of is gone before, and wee muſt fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowe after, God graunt vs all of his grace: Of the deade wee are taught (you know) to ſay the beſt: howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer it is, it ſhalbe good for you to haue an eye to your ſelues and your owne eſtates, and not to ſtand thus gazing and gaping vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> others with whom yee haue nothing to doe: ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie your ſelues peceablie as becom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſober women. For though I ſhewe you favour nowe, yee muſt think I can not doe ſo alwayes: I am overlooked my ſelfe, &amp; thereby you know, can not doe whatI would.</hi>
               </p>
            </sp>
            <sp>
               <speaker>Woman.</speaker>
               <p>The man (you ſay) is gone before and wee must follow after: You doe not meane I hope thereby that we must followe Ma. <hi>Turne-penie</hi> either in his ſteppes in this
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:6302:37"/>life, or in his ende and destinie when hee went out of this life. In either of theſe I tell you, wee would be loth to followe him, and I trust GOD in mercie will ſhield vs from it. We must (you ſay) haue an eye to our ſelues, and not ſtande gazing and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping vpon others: and yet ſo to looke vpon others, namelie vpon David as an exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of mercie, or vpon Saul as an example of iudgement, that thereby wee may reape profitt and benefit to our ſelues, is not (I thinke) either daungerous or vnlawfull. That which I ſpake of the man was not of malice, I aſſure you, for I knowe him not: but for a Caveat and warning to ſuch as you are to beware of the like practiſe, least you be overtaken with the like iudgement. He ſommoned for trifles, and ſo doe you. He proſecuted &amp; purſued the best and the holiest men, and ſo doe you. Hee laughed and gyred and made a ſcoffe when he was tolde of his fault, and ſo doe you. He came to a fearfull and lamentable ende, and ſo
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:6302:37"/>(without repentance while mercie is offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red) may you. But you are overlooked, you ſay: if it be ſo in deede, I am not ſorie for it: for I could wiſh that you and your over-lookers were better over-looked then you bee, and then it were happie, and thrice happie for our Church. The best is, (and therein is our onelie comfort) There is one that over-lookes vs all, and bridles both you and your overlookers: otherwiſe it were double woe with vs. To his bleſſed direction (with thankes for this time) I leaue you. And ſo praying you not to ſende for one againe in haste (wiſhing my ſelf at home, and you a better office &amp; occupation to thrine by then this) I bidde you farewell.</p>
            </sp>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
